Register of the John W. Nason Papers, 1921-2001
Hoover Institution Archives
John W. Nason Papers,
1921-2001
83003
Nason, John W.
51 manuscript boxes, 1 envelope (21.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, minutes, memoranda, newsletters, leaflets, and financial statements, relating to the work of the National Japanese American Student Relocation Council in placing Japanese American students in colleges and universities in the United States during World War II, and to other aspects of education in the United States.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1983.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
National Japanese American Student Relocation Council records, Hoover Institution Archives
Gertrude King papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Thomas Ray Bodine papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Access Points
Education; Japanese Americans--Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945; World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945--Education and the war; Education--United States; World War, 1939-1945--United States
Biographical Note
1905, Feb. 9 Born, St. Paul, Minnesota
1931-1940 Instructor and Assistant Professor, Swarthmore College
1938-1939 Chairman, Department of Philosophy, Swarthmore College
1940-1953 President, Swarthmore College
1942-1945 Chairman, National Japanese-American Student Relocation Council
1942-1945 President, UN Council of Philadelphia
1943-1949 President, National Council on Religion in Higher Education
1945-1978 Trustee, Edward W. Hazen Foundation
1949-1953 President, World Affairs Council of Philadelphia
1953-1962 President, Foreign Policy Association
1962-1970 President, Carleton College
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, minutes, memoranda, newsletters, leaflets, and financial statements, relating to the work of the National Japanese American Student Relocation Council in placing Japanese American students in colleges and universities in the United States during World War II, and to other aspects of education in the United States.
Container List
- Biographical File, 1926-1979. (Box 1)
  Printed articles, serial issues, correspondence, awards, trip material, memoranda, clippings, notes, newsletters, and miscellany relating to the life of John William Nason, arranged chronologically.
  - Printed articles, serial issues, correspondence, memoranda, clippings, notes, newsletters, awards, trip material, and miscellany (Box 1., Folder 1-9)
- Speeches and Writings, 1931-1989. (Box 2-12)
  Typescript and printed copies of writings by John W. Nason, arranged chronologically.
  - Undated (Box 1., Folder 10)
  - 1931-1937 (Folder 11)
  - 1937-1942 (Box 2., Folder 1-6)
  - 1942-1944 (Box 3., Folder 1-5)
  - 1944-1947 (Box 4., Folder 1-6)
  - 1947-1952 (Box 5., Folder 1-7)
  - 1952-1956 (Box 6., Folder 1-6)
  - 1957-1962 (Box 7., Folder 1-7)
  - 1963-1965 (Box 8., Folder 1-3)
  - 1965-1968 (Box 9., Folder 1-4)
  - 1968-1974 (Box 10., Folder 1-5)
  - 1974-1981 (Box 11., Folder 1-5)
  - 1982-1989 (Box 12., Folder 1-2)
- Correspondence, 1926-1988. (Box 12-19)
  Correspondence and other material generally relating to educational and philanthropic organizations and activities; also includes some personal correspondence. Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - General. Letters of congratulation, 1940 (Box 12., Folder 3-5)
  - General. Letters of congratulation, 1953-1962 (Box 13.)
  - A - Miscellaneous, 1931-1978 (Box 14., Folder 1)
  - Armstrong, James and Carol, 1976-1989 (Folder 2)
  - B - Miscellaneous, 1968-1984 (Folder 3)
  - Bean, Atherton, 1970-1988 (Folder 4)
  - Blanshard, Brand, 1931-1989 (Folder 5)
  - Bowen, Howard R., 1973-1986 (Folder 6)
  - Boyer, Ernest L., 1975-1987 (Folder 7)
  - Bradley, William L., 1982-1986 (Folder 8)
  - Braisted, Paul J., 1973-1981 (Folder 9)
  - Brewster, Kingman, 1975-1985 (Folder 10)
  - Brown, David G., 1978-1979 (Folder 11)
  - Burke, Joseph C., 1980-1989 (Folder 12)
  - Burn, Barbara B., 1978-1980 (Folder 13)
  - C - Miscellaneous, 1931-1989 (Box 15., Folder 1)
  - Cowling, Donald J., 1926-1940 (Folder 2)
  - Cuninggim, Merrimon, 1972-1986 (Folder 3)
  - D - Miscellaneous, 1931-1988 (Folder 4)
  - E - Miscellaneous, 1964-1989 (Folder 5)
  - Eisenhower, Milton, 1960-1972 (Folder 6)
  - Enarson, Harold L., 1973-1974 (Folder 7)
  - F - Miscellaneous, 1969-1981 (Folder 8)
  - Fisher, Dorothy Canfield, 1935-1955 (Folder 9)
  - Friend, Theodore, 1981-1986 (Box 16., Folder 1)
  - G - Miscellaneous, 1942-1977 (Folder 2)
  - Gale, Robert L., 1973-1988 (Folder 3)
  - Gould, Lawrence, 1954-1962 (Folder 4)
  - Greenleaf, Robert K., 1973-1986 (Folder 5)
  - H - Miscellaneous, 1971-1987 (Folder 6)
  - Holderman, James B., 1976-1977 (Folder 7)
  - Holt, Rush D., 1972-1989 (Folder 8)
  - Hunt, Everett L., 1961-1981 (Folder 9)
  - I - Miscellaneous, 1967-1982 (Folder 10)
  - J - Miscellaneous, 1967-1988 (Folder 11)
  - K - Miscellaneous, 1969-1987 (Folder 12)
  - Kauffman, Joseph F., 1974-1987 (Box 17., Folder 1)
  - Kerr, Clark, 1969-1985 (Folder 2)
  - Kipanta, Nestor E., 1977-1979 (Folder 3)
  - L - Miscellaneous, 1936-1987 (Folder 4)
  - Lavender, David G., 1971-1987 (Folder 5)
  - M - Miscellaneous, 1965-1987 (Folder 6)
  - Perkins, James A., 1960-1988 (Box 18., Folder 1)
  - O - Miscellaneous, 1974-1985 (Folder 2)
  - P - Miscellaneous, 1969-1989 (Folder 3)
  - Paltridge, J.G., 1973-1980 (Folder 4)
  - Porter, David H., 1986-1987 (Folder 5)
  - R - Miscellaneous, 1951-1988 (Folder 6)
  - Riesman, David, 1975-1986 (Folder 7)
  - S- Miscellaneous, 1959-1988 (Folder 8)
  - St. Lawrence University, 1971-1974 (Folder 9)
  - Streit, Clarence, 1978-1979 (Folder 10)
  - Sherrill, Henry, 1974-1980 (Folder 11)
  - T - Miscellaneous, 1964-1988 (Folder 12)
  - Trudeau Institute, 1980-1984 (Folder 13)
  - V - Miscellaneous, 1940-1984 (Box 19., Folder 1)
  - W - Miscellaneous, 1934-1988 (Folder 2)
  - Wood, Miriam M., 1982-1986 (Folder 3)
  - Y - Miscellaneous, 1969-1989 (Folder 4)
  - Z - Miscellaneous, 1931-1988 (Folder 5)
- National Japanese-American Student Relocation Council, 1942-1946. (Box 19-22)
  Correspondence, financial reports, progress reports, student materials and procedures, meeting minutes, and miscellany relating to efforts to place relocated Japanese-American students in colleges in the U.S. during World War II. Arranged by physical form.
  - Correspondence, Internal (Box 19., Folder 6)
    - General
    - American Friends Service Committee (AFSC), 1942-1945 Financial memoranda (including AFSC)
      - 1942
      - 1943 (Folder 7)
      - 1944
      - 1945
    - National Japanese-American Student Relocation Council
      - 1942 Jan.-Sept. (Folder 8)
      - 1942 Oct.-Nov. (Folder 9)
      - 1942 Dec. (Folder 10)
      - 1943 Jan.-Feb. (Box 20., Folder 1)
      - 1943 March-Dec. (Folder 2)
      - 1944 Jan.-May (Folder 3)
      - 1944 June-Dec. (Folder 4)
      - 1945-1946 (Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, General
    - General (Folder 6)
    - Church Organizations (includes correspondence regarding funding), 1942-1945
      - American Baptist Home Mission
      - B'nai B'rith Hillel Foundation
      - Brethren Service Committee
      - Congregational Christian Churches of the U.S.A., The Council for Social Action
      - Evangelican and Reformed Church, Board of National Missions
      - Federal Council of Churches
      - Fellowship of Reconciliation
      - Interseminary Movement
      - Jesuit Educational Association
      - Mennonite Central Committee
      - Methodist Church
        - Board of Education
        - Board of Missions and Church Extension
      - Presbyterian Church
        - Board of Education
        - Board of National Missions
      - Protestant Church Commission for Japanese Service
      - Protestant Episcopal Church, National Council
      - Reformed Church in America, Board of Education (Folder 7)
      - Southern Baptist Convention, Board of Foreign Missions
      - National Council of Student Christian Associations (including Young Women's Christian Association)
    - Funding Organizations and Individuals, 1942-1945
      - Individuals
        - Hadley, Morris
        - Kaltenborn, H.V.
        - McDonald, Malcolm B. (regarding Charles Ward)
        - Moore, Hugh
        - Morris, Roland S. (includes list of U.S. firms with an interest in Japan)
        - Stafford, Mrs. Bradley E.
        - Taft, Henry W.
        - Turner, J. Archer
      - Foundations
        - Barbour Foundation
        - Carnegie Corporation (includes proposal)
        - Columbia Foundation (Mrs. Charles DeYoung Elkus)
        - Ford Foundation (Folder 8)
        - Hazen Foundation
        - McGregor Fund
        - Rockefeller Foundation (Folder 9)
        - Julius Rosenwald Fund
        - William C. Whitney Foundation
    - Governmental Organizations (Box 21., Folder 1)
      - General
        - Congress
          - Senate Judiciary Committee (Patrick A. McCarran, Chairman)
          - House Judiciary Committee (Hatton W. Sumners)
        - Federal Security Agency (Charles P. Taft)
      - Department of Justice (Earl. G. Harrison, Commissioner)
      - Department of Labor, National War Labor Board (Frank Porter Graham)
      - Department of the Navy
        - Special Assistant to the Secretary (Adlai E. Stevenson)
        - Bureau of Naval Personnel (Rear Admiral Randall Jacobs, Chief)
      - Department of State
        - Acting Secretary (Joseph C. Grew)
        - Walter M. Kotschnig
      - Department of War
        - Office of Assistant Secretary (John J. McCloy, Assistant Secretary)
        - Office of the Adjutant General
        - Office of the Provost Marshal General
          - General
          - Japanese American Branch (Capt. Clarence Harbert, Chief)
          - Personnel Security Division (Col. Alton C. Miller, Director)
          - Office for Emergency Management, War Manpower Commission
        - Office of War Information (Milton S. Eisenhower, Associate Director) SEE ALSO: Correspondence, General/Universities and Colleges/Kansas, State College of Agriculture and Applied Science
        - War Relocation Authority
          - General
          - Office of the Director (Dillon S. Myer, Director; E.M. Rowell, Deputy Director)
          - Community Analysis Section (John F. Embree, Head) (Folder 2)
          - Community Management Division (John H. Provinse, Chief)
          - Employment Division (Thomas W. Holland, Chief)
          - Reports and Publications Division (John C. Baker, Chief)
          - Regional Offices and Camps
            - General
            - Colorado River Project, Poston, Arizona
            - Gila River Project, Rivers, Arizona
            - Granada Project, Amache, Colorado
            - Heart Mountain Project, Heart Mountain, Wyoming
            - Manzanar Project, Manzanar, California
            - Minidoka Project, Hunt, Idaho
            - Rohwer Project, McGehee, Arkansas
    - Press Correspondence
    - Student Correspondence
      - General (Folder 3)
      - Individual Students
    - Universities and Academic Organizations, 1942-1945 (Folder 4)
      - General
        - Association of American Colleges (Guy E. Snavely, Member, Exec. Comm., NJASRC)
        - Baptist Hospital, Alexandria, Louisiana
        - Institute for Advanced Study (Frank Aydelotte)
      - Form letters
      - Individual Institutions
        - Arizona State Teachers College (J.O. Grimes, Dean)
        - Bates College
        - Baylor University
        - Beaver College
        - Boston University (Daniel L. Marsh, President)
        - Bowdoin College (Kenneth H. Sills, President)
        - Brown University (Henry Wriston, President)
        - Bryn Mawr College
        - Bucknell University (Arnaud C. Marts, President)
        - Buffalo, University of (Edward S. Jones, Dean)
        - California, University of
          - Deutsch, Monroe E., Vice-President and Provost (also Member West Coast Advisory Committee, NJASRC; more extensive correspondence)
          - Kingman, Harry L.
          - Sproul, Robert G. (Member, West Coast Advisory Committee, NJASRC)
          - Thomas, Dorothy Swaine, Director, Evacuation and Resettlement Study
        - Carleton College (Donald J. Cowling, President; Lindsey Blayney, Dean) (Folder 5)
        - Chicago, University of (Robert Redfield, Dean; Emery T. Filbey, Vice-President)
        - Cincinnati, University of (Raymond Walters, President)
        - Colorado, University of
        - Columbia University, School of Education, School of Journalism (Carl Ackerman, Dean)
        - Cornell University (Edmund Ezra Day, President)
        - Dakota Wesleyan University
        - Denison University (Kenneth I. Brown, President)
        - Denver, University of (Caleb F. Gates, Chancellor)
        - DePauw University (Edward R. Bartlett, Dean)
        - Drake University
        - Drexel Institute of Technology (D.C. Disque, Dean)
        - Fisk University (Thomas E. Jones, President)
        - George Williams College (H.C. Coffman, President)
        - Gettysburg College
        - Grinnell College (Shelton L. Beatty, Dean)
        - Hamilton College (W.H. Cowley, President)
        - Harvard University (George H. Chase, Dean)
        - Haverford College (Archibald McIntosh, Vice-President)
        - Howard University (Mordecai W. Johnson, President)
        - Illinois Institute of Technology (J.C. Peebles, Dean)
        - Iowa, State University of (Virgil Hancher, President)
        - Kansas, State College of Agriculture and Applied Science (Milton S. Eisenhower, President) SEE ALSO Correspondence, General/Government Organizations/Office of War Information
        - Kenyon College (Gordon K. Chalmers, President)
        - Knox College (Carter Davidson, President; more extensive correspondence)
        - Linfield College (Harry L. Dillin, President)
        - Manchester College (V.F. Schwalm, President)
        - Mary Hardin-Baylor College (Gordon G. Singleton, President)
        - Maryland State Teachers College
        - Massachusetts State College (Hugh P. Baker, President)
        - Michigan, University of (E. Blythe Stason, President)
        - Milwaukee State Teachers College (Frank E. Baker, President)
        - Milwaukee Vocational School (William F. Rashe, Director)
        - Morris Harvey College (R.L. Riggleman, President)
        - Mount Holyoke College
        - Multnomah College (George Allen Odgers, Dean)
        - Nebraska Wesleyan University (Benjamin F. Schwartz, Chancellor)
        - New Hampshire, University of (Fred Engelhardt, President)
        - New York, College of the City of (H.N. Wright, President)
        - Northwestern University (Franklyn B. Snyder, President)
        - Oberlin College (Ernest H. Wilkins, President) (Folder 6)
        - Oregon, University of (Karl W. Onthank, Dean)
        - Park College (William L. Young, President)
        - Pennsylvania, University of (H. Sherman Oberly, President)
        - Randolph Macon Woman's College (Theodore H. Jack, President)
        - Reed College (Arthur F. Scott, Acting President)
        - St. Lawrence University (Harold E.B. Speight, Dean)
        - Sarah Lawrence College
        - Scripps College
        - Smith College (Herbert Davis, President)
        - Southern California, University of (Lewis E. Ford, Dean, College of Dentistry)
        - Spelman College
        - Stanford University
          - Ray Lyman Wilbur, President
          - Edwin A. Cottrell, Professor of Political Science
        - Susquehanna University (G. Morris Smith, President)
        - Swarthmore College
        - Syracuse University (Frank Piskor, Acting Dean)
        - Temple University
        - Tufts College
        - Union College (Dixon Ryan Fox, President)
        - Vanderbilt University (O.C. Carmichael, Chancellor)
        - Vassar College
        - Washington, University of (L.P. Sieg, President; Robert W. O'Brien, Assistant to President, later Executive Director, NJASRC; Edward H. Lauer, Dean)
        - Washington and Jefferson College (Melvin D. Brewer, Dean)
        - Wesleyan University
        - West Chester State Teachers College (Charles Swope, President)
        - Western Reserve University (Winifred G. Leutner, President)
        - West Virginia, University of (Charles R. Lawall, President)
        - Wilmington College (S.A. Watson, President)
        - Wisconsin, University of (Clarence A. Dykstra, President)
  - Organization and Goals (Folder 7)
    - Report of initial conference regarding establishment of NJASRC
    - Statements of purpose, program and procedures
    - Periodic reassessments of goals, discussion of termination
  - Administration and Procedures (Folder 8)
    - General
    - Personnel
      - Employees
      - Potential employees
      - Search for directors
    - Student Materials and Procedures (Box 22., Folder 1)
      - General
        - General
        - Lists of schools
        - Student security clearances
        - Forms
        - Statistics, graphs and charts
        - Student records
        - Form letters (for correspondence with specific students SEE ALSO Correspondence, General/Students)
      - Procedures
    - Minutes of Meetings, 1942-1946 (Folder 2)
      - General
      - Executive Committee Meetings
      - General Council Meetings
    - Reports, 1942-1946 (Folder 3)
      - Progress reports
      - Field reports (Folder 4)
      - Student newsletters
      - Meetings reports
      - Telephone conversations
      - Financial reports (Folder 5)
        - Monthly financial reports
        - Quarterly financial reports
        - Cumulative financial reports
        - External audits
        - Budget estimates
        - Church commitments (Folder 6)
        - Scholarship reports
        - Student returnee project reports
- Edward W. Hanzen Foundation File, 1971-1987. (Box 23-24)
  Correspondence, copies of proposals submitted for consideration by the foundation, minutes of meetings and other miscellaneous materials relating to John W. Nason's role as trustee of the foundation. Arranged by physical form.
  - General. By-laws, notes, statements of interest, information on the Mary Reynolds Babcock Foundation (Box 23., Folder 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Internal, 1973-1977
    - Individual, 1971-1987 (Folder 2)
      - General
      - Armstrong, James I.
      - Babbidge, Homer D., Jr.
      - Bailey, Adrienne Y.
      - Bradley, William L. (President, Hazen Fdn., extensive correspondence) (Folder 2-3)
      - Braisted, Paul J. (Folder 4)
      - Chabrier, Jacques R.
      - Comer, James P.
      - Compton, Randolph P.
      - Cuninggim, A. Merrimon
      - Dixon, John
      - Duggan, Stephen P.
      - Fairfax, Jean
      - Foster, Marcus A.
      - Glover, Milton H.
      - Gray, Hanna H.
      - Haviland, H. Field, Jr.
      - Hazen, David C.
      - Holden, Reuben A.
      - Holland, Jerome H.
      - Loescher, Samuel M. (Folder 5)
      - Magat, Richard
      - Morgan, Kenneth W.
      - Riesman, David
      - Shedd, Mark
      - Sherburne, Mary Lela
      - Sonthoff, Herbert
      - Truman, David B.
      - Turner, A. Richard
      - Wolf, Mary Hunter
      - Ylvisaker, Paul N.
      - Zucker, Mildred
  - Proposals (includes correspondence) (Folder 6)
  - Cultural Relations for the Future (Study Group), 1970-1972 (Folder 7-8)
    - General (progress reports, meeting reports, analytical reports)
    - Correspondence
  - Committee on Forward Planning, 1970-1971 (Folder 8)
    - General
    - Correspondence
  - Meeting Minutes, 1971-1982
    - General (Box 24., Folder 1)
    - Annual (Spring) Meetings (Folder 1-9)
    - Autumn Meetings (Folder 10-14)
- Subject File, 1929-1988. (Box 25-38)
  Pamphlets, newspaper clippings, leaflets, bulletins, newsletters, agency reports, typed copies of printed matter, press releases, speech transcripts, legal briefs, and miscellany, relating predominately to the issue of Japanese-American internment during World War II. Also includes material on miltary service of Japanese, correspondence relating to the position of conscientious objectors involved in the student relocation project, and statements regarding the Dies Committee investigation. Arranged alphabetically by topic.
  - Academy for Educational Development. Conference material, correspondence, printed material, and miscellany, 1979-1986 (Box 25., Folder 1-2)
  - Academy for Senior Professionals. Correspondence, by-laws, pamphlet, and miscellany, 1983-1988 (Folder 3)
  - Adirondack North Country Association. Correspondence and miscellany, 1973-1987 (Folder 4-5)
  - Alliss Educational Foundation. Correspondence, reports, minutes, and miscellany, 1977 (Folder 6)
  - American Council on Education. Correspondence and conference material, 1978-1984 (Folder 7-11)
  - American Friends Service Committee. Correspondence, memoranda, agenda and minutes, and conference material, 1956-1973 (Folder 12-13)
  - Assocation of Governing Boards of Universities and Colleges. Correspondence, notes, conference material, reports, printed material, grant proposals, speeches, memoranda, questionnaire, biographical sketches, and miscellany, 1973-1987. Includes material relating to specific institutions (Folder 14-26)
  - Association of Governing Boards of Universities and Colleges (Box 26., Folder 1-23)
  - Association of Governing Boards of Universities and Colleges (Box 27., Folder 1-22)
  - Association of Governing Boards of Universities and Colleges (Box 28., Folder 1-21)
  - Association of Governing Boards of Universities and Colleges (Box 29., Folder 1-3)
  - Association of Governing Boards of Universities and Colleges (Box 30., Folder 1-13)
  - Association of Governing Boards of Universities and Colleges (Box 31., Folder 1-13)
  - Aspen Institute. Correspondence, memoranda, and conference material, 1959-1984 (Folder 14-16)
  - Carleton College. Correspondence, speeches, printed material, 1960-1964 (Folder 17-19)
  - Carleton College, 1969-1986 (Box 32., Folder 1-3)
  - Center for Music, Drama and Art. Correspondence, memoranda, and notes, 1977-1980 (Folder 4)
  - Center for War and Peace Studies. Correspondence and flyer, 1972-1979 (Folder 5)
  - Century Club. Correspondence and biographical sketches, 1972-1988 (Folder 6)
  - Charities Aid Foundation. Correspondence, notes, and miscellany, 1978-1979 (Folder 7)
  - City University of New York. Correspondence, notes, meeting agenda and minutes, 1981-1983 (Folder 8)
  - Committee for an Effective and Durable Peace in Asia. Correspondence, memoranda, and printed material, 1965-1970 (Folder 9)
  - Conference Board (organization). Correspondence, notes, and printed material, 1973-1984 (Folder 10)
  - Conference of Southwest Foundations. Correspondence and notes, 1977 (Folder 11)
  - Council for the Advancement of Small Colleges. Correspondence, notes, and survey results, 1978-1980 (Folder 12)
  - Council of Michigan Foundations. Correspondence, notes, and printed material, 1976-1981 (Folder 13)
  - Council on Foundations. Correspondence, memoranda, conference material, notes, printed material, miscellany, 1976-1984 (Folder 14-17)